让我们来完成这些练习。
Let's go through these exercises.
我们将讨论免费的 monads、镜头和使用任何东西构建应用程序
And we'll talk about free monads, lenses and getting to app building with whatever
时间我们已经离开了我们可以构建的几个应用程序。
time we have left for a couple of apps we can build.
所以我只是要快点完成这个但绝对阻止我
So I'm just gonna go through this a little quickly but definitely stop me and
我会在我们走的时候回答任何问题。
I'll answer any questions as we go.
所以我们用函数要么问。
So we use function either ask.
由于我们在函数类型中，
Since we're in the function type,
我们有一个我们之前看到的 ask 方法来获得这个配置。
we have a ask method we saw earlier to get at this configuration.
然后返回端口，好吗？
And then return the port, okay?
所以我会说 function 或者.ask，这是一个实际的函数类型。
So I'll say function either.ask, and that is an actual function type.
所以现在我可以映射它并进入配置，进入 config.port。
So now I can map over that and get to the config, get to config.port.
它有效，很酷。
And it works, cool.
不太难，但我只是凭空拉出配置。
Not too hard, but I just pull the config out of thin air.
它很甜。
It's pretty sweet.
让我们更进一步。
Let's take it a little further.
现在它说，使用示例一获取端口并连接到数据库。
Now it says, use example one to get the port and connect to the db.
然后我们会发现这个想法是什么。
And then we're gonna find whatever this idea is.
所以，就在这里使用示例一，调用它，它会给我
So, just use example one here, call that, it'll give me
获取的端口 - 所以这当然不是端口号。
the port to get the- so this, of course is not the port number.
我当然不应该说，但这仍然在一个函数中，对吧？
I shouldn't say of course, but this is still inside a function either, right?
我们只是映射了它并更改了里面的值来保存端口。
We just mapped it and changed the value inside to hold the port.
所以我们有一个函数要么持有一个端口。
So we have a function either holding a port.
所以我们调用它来映射它以获取端口。
So we call that to map over that to get the port.
整洁，然后从那里开始，我们必须做什么？
Neat, and then from there, what do we have to do?
我们想连接到数据库，所以我们连接到数据库，它需要一个端口。
We want to connect to the db, so we have connect to db, that takes a port.
然后这让我回归。
And then that returns me in either.
的fakeDb 或离开未能连接。
Of the fakeDb or left to failed to connect.
我也有一个函数，我试图映射它并返回一个。
I have a function either, and I'm trying to map over that and return an either.
那么我也有一个功能。
So then I'll have a function either either.
所以我们不想那样做，我们想要锁链然后我们想要举起，
So we don't wanna do that, we wanna chain and then we wanna lift,
这要么进入功能要么，看看是否正常？
This either into the function either, see if that's going all right?
最后一件事是找到 id。
And the last thing is find the id.
我们有 id，我们有一个 fakeDb。
We have the id, we have a fakeDb.
现在我们有了它，我们应该有一个 db.
Now that we have that, we should have a db.
然后，我们想找到 db.find(id)。
And then, we wanna find db.find(id).
糟糕，它还有另一个。
Crap, it's got another either.
[笑] 链条的一部分。
[LAUGH] Part of the chain.
我们将不得不举起。
And we'll have to lift.
让我们看看是否做到了。
Let's see if that did it.
嘿，那过去了。
Hey, that passed.
人们是否明白为什么我不喜欢 monad 变压器？
Are people seeing why I don't like monad transformers?
[笑] 但它们无处不在
[LAUGH] But they're everywhere and
他们——也许他们更有意义。
they're- perhaps they make more sense.
我可能会根据这些东西做出不公平的判断。
I might be making an unfair judgement based on this stuff is fine.
基于 Javascript 因素的不公平判断。
Unfair judgement based on factor in Javascript.
我们没有很多类型帮助之类的东西，
And we don't have a lot of type help and stuff like that,
但它们在任何语言中都非常痛苦。
but they're pretty painful in any language.
练习二。
Exercise two.
让我们进入ReaderTask，有趣。
Let's go into ReaderTask, fun.
我们有一个函数，持有一个任务。
We have a function, holding a task.
我只是在这里称它为读者，因为这通常就是你所说的函数。
I just called it reader here because that's usually what you call function.
我们将再次请求获取 postUrl 的服务器。
And we're gonna ask again to get the server for the postUrl.
并从 ReaderTask 获取服务器变量。
And get the server variable from ReaderTask.
男孩，这里到底发生了什么？
Boy, what's even happening here?
[笑] 真的让我们为成功做好了准备。
[LAUGH] Really sets us up for success y'all.
所以看起来服务器没有定义。
So it looks like server is not defined.
我们需要得到服务器。
We need to get the server.
所以我调用 ReaderTask.ask，我们将链接它以获取服务器。
So I call ReaderTask.ask, and we'll chain over that to get the server.
我可以映射。
And I could have mapped.
但我马上就知道里面的这个东西，
But I know right off the bat that this thing inside,
它正在取物，这将是一项任务。
it's doing a fetch, it's gonna be a task.
所以我可能只需要遍历 ReaderTask 来提升这个东西。
So I'll probably have to just loop through ReaderTask that lift this thing.
那样有用吗？
Does that work?
就是这样，很酷，所以，这有点 - 我们正在谈论
There it is, cool, so, that is a little bit of a- we're talking
关于从 reader monad 中获取内容，
about getting stuff out of the reader monad,
我们试图把东西放进去，但我们保持肤浅。
we're trying to put stuff in and we're staying shallow.
所以这里没有我们在这里看到的那么糟糕。
So it's not as bad here as what we saw over here.
但我只是想对使用这些东西有一点感觉。
But I just wanna get a little bit of a feel to use these things.
因此，当我们非常严格时，我们可以使用它作为构建应用程序的工具——
And so we can use this as a tool to build apps when we have very rigid-
还有一个，看看那个[笑]。
there's another one, look at that [LAUGH].
好像已经过去了。
Looks like it's already passing.
为了节省时间，我不想这样做，我只是跳过了这个。
In the interest of time, I don't wanna do this, I just skipped this one.
我可以稍后发布答案。
I could post the answer later.
但这试图解释的是我们一起做了什么。
But what this is trying to explain is what we did together.
它有这些帖子，然后我们折叠。
It's got these either posts, then we're folding.
我们更愿意做的是使用 Api2，它返回一个 TaskEither 和
And what we'd rather do is use Api2, which returns us a TaskEither and
它只会清理整个事情。
it would just clean this whole thing up.
所以它显示了它们真正闪耀的地方。
So it shows where they actually shine.
让我们做吧，为什么不呢？
Let's do it, why not?
[笑]你拉了我的腿。
[LAUGH] You pulled my leg.
所以在这里我们只是得到了这个帖子。
So here we just get the post.
等等，在这种情况下，那个点刺有意义吗[笑]？
Wait, does that dot sting make sense [LAUGH] in this context?
[笑]让我拉我的手臂。
[LAUGH] Made me pull my arm.
我们有 Api2 get post。
And we have Api2 get post.
然后我们得到一个帖子。
And then we get a post out.
而不是所有这些，我们可以只获取帖子标题并完成它。
Instead of all this, we could just get the post title and be done with it.
那样有用吗？
Does that work?
它有效，很酷。
It works, cool.
所以你可以看到 Api2 更好，因为当我映射和链接时，我得到了帖子或
So you can see Api2 is much nicer because as I map and chain, I get at the post or
无论它持有什么，而不是介于两者之间的中间类型。
whatever it's holding, not the intermediate types in between.
如果你确实有一个类型，比如数据库的东西
And if you do have a type, like a database thing and
你做一个任务，他们确实有一个地方，他们不是那么糟糕。
you make a TaskEither, they do have a place where they're not so bad.
真的是当你开始有四五种类型时，你会返回不同的
It's really when you start to have four or five types, you're returning different
类型，您必须将它们放在正确的插槽中等等。
types and you have to put them in the right slots and so on.